I was born in Switzerland
لقد ولدت في سويسرا
and raised in Ghana, West Africa.
ونشأت في غانا، في غرب أفريقيا.
Ghana felt safe to me as a child.
كطفل شعرت بأن غانا مكان آمن بالنسبة لي.
I was free, I was happy.
كنت حر، وسعيد.
The early 70s
بدايات حقبة السبعينات
marked a time of musical and artistic excellence in Ghana.
شهدت فترة إزدهار الموسيقى والفن في غانا.
But then by the end of the decade,
لكن بنهاية العقد،
the country had fallen back into political instability
شهدت البلد عدم استقرار سياسي
and mismanagement.
وفساد إداري.
In 1979,
في عام 1979م،
I witnessed my first military coup.
شهدتُ بنفسي أول إنقلاب عسكري.
We the children had gathered at a friend's house.
تجمعنا نحن الأطفال في منزل أحد الأصدقاء.
It was a dimly lit shack.
إنه كوخ به ضوء خافت.
There was a beaten up black and white television
كان هناك تلفزيون من النوع الأبيض والأسود
flickering in the background,
يتأرحج في خلفية الكوخ،
and a former head of state and general
الرئيس والجنرال السابق
was being blindfolded
معصوب العنين
and tied to the pole.
ومربوط على العمود.
The firing squad aimed, fired --
أطلق الرصاص، بهدف تنفيذ عملية الأعدام رميا بالرصاص --
the general was dead.
ومات الجنرال.
Now this was being broadcast live.
لقد كانت هذه العملية تبث مباشرة.
And shortly after, we left the country,
وبعدها بفترة قصيرة، غادرنا البلاد،
and we returned to Switzerland.
وعدنا إلى سويسرا.
Now Europe came as a shock to me,
والآن جاءت أوروبا لتمثل صدمة بالنسبة لي،
and I think I started feeling the need
وأعتقد أنني بدأت أشعر بالحاجة
to shed my skin in order to fit in.
لتغيير بشرتي لتكون مناسبة.
I wanted to blend in like a chameleon.
رغبت أن أتلون مثل الحرباء.
I think it was a tactic of survival.
أعتقد أنه كان تكتيك للبقاء.
And it worked, or so I believed.
وأنه جاء بنتيجة، أو على ما أعتقد ذلك.
So here I was in 2008
كان ذلك في عام 2008
wondering where I was in my life.
حيث تساءلت أين كنت في حياتي.
And I felt I was being typecast as an actor.
وشعرت بأنني كنت كائن يؤدي دورا كالممثل.
I was always playing the exotic African.
كنت دائما ألعب دور الأفريقي الغريب.
I was playing the violent African,
كنت ألعب دور الأفريقي العنيف،
the African terrorist.
الأفريقي الإرهابي.
And I was thinking,
وكنت أفكر،
how many terrorists could I possibly play
كم يمكنني أن أقوم بدور الإرهابيين
before turning into one myself?
قبل أن أتحول بنفسي إلى واحد منهم؟
And I had become ashamed of the other,
وها قد أصبحت استحي من الأخرى،
the African in me.
أصولي الأفريقي.
And fortunately I decided in 2008
ولحسن الحظ ففي عام 2008م قررتُ
to return to Ghana,
العودة إلى غانا،
after 28 years of absence.
بعد غياب دام 28 عاما.
I wanted to document on film
كنت أرغب في تصوير فيلم وثائقي
the 2008 presidential elections.
عن الإنتخابات الرئاسية في عام 2008م.
And there, I started by searching
وعندما وصلت إلى هناك، بدأت بالبحث
for the footprints in my childhood.
عن بقايا الآثار لفترة طفولتي.
And before I even knew it,
وقبل أن أعرف ذلك،
I was suddenly on a stage
وجدت نفسي فجأة على منصة
surrounded by thousands of cheering people
محاطة بالآلآف من الناس يهتفون
during a political rally.
أثناء تجمع سياسي.
And I realized that, when I'd left the country,
وأدركت أنه، عندما غادرت البلاد،
free and fair elections in a democratic environment
الحرية والإنتخابات النزيهة في مناخ ديمقراطي
were a dream.
كانت حلما.
And now that I'd returned, that dream had become reality,
وها الآن ربما أعود، ليتحقق ذلك الحلم على أرض الواقع،
though a fragile reality.
برغم ضعف الواقع
And I was thinking,
وأنا أفكر،
was Ghana searching for its identity
هل تبحث غانا عن هويتها
like I was looking for my identity?
مثل ما أنا أبحث عن هويتي؟
Was what was happening in Ghana a metaphor
هل ما يحدث في غانا هو مجازاً
for what was happening in me?
لما يحدث لي؟
And it was as if through the standards of my Western life,
و كأنها بمعايير حياتي في الغرب،
I hadn't lived up to my full potential.
التي لم أعيشها بكل إمكانياتي وطاقتي.
I mean, nor had Ghana,
كذلك لم تفعل غانا،
even though we had been trying very hard.
برغم محاولاتنا الجادة.
Now in 1957,
في عام 1957،
Ghana was the first sub-Saharan country
كانت غانا أول دولة أفريقية جنوب الصحراء الكبرى
to gain its independence.
تحصل على إستقلالها.
In the late 50s,
في أواخر الخمسينات،
Ghana and Singapore had the same GDP.
تساوى إجمالي الناتج المحلي لغانا وسنغافورة.
I mean, today, Singapore is a First World country
الآن، سنغافورة هي دولة من الطراز العالمي الأول،
and Ghana is not.
بينما غانا ليست بنفس المستوى.
But maybe it was time to prove to myself,
لكن ربما حان الوقت لأثبت لنفسي،
yes, it's important to understand the past,
نعم، أنه من الأهمية فهم الماضي،
it is important to look at it in a different light,
ومن المهم النظر إليه من منظور مختلف،
but maybe we should look at the strengths in our own culture
ربما يجب علينا النظر إلى مظاهر القوة في ثقافنتا
and build on those foundations in the present.
والبناء على هذه الأسس في الوقت الحاضر.
So here I was, December 7th, 2008.
وها أنا في يوم ، 7 ديسمبر 2008.
The polling stations opened to the voters at 7:00 AM,
فتحت مراكز الإقتراع للناخبين في الساعة 7 صباحا،
but voters, eager to take their own political fate into their hands,
لكن الناخبين، حريصون لتسوية مصيرهم السياسي بأيديهم،
were starting to line up at 4:00 AM in the morning.
حيث بداوا يقفون في صفوف منذ الساعة الرابعة صباحا.
And they had traveled from near, they had traveled from far,
لقد جاءوا من جميع المناطق القريبة والبعيدة،
because they wanted to make their voices heard.
لرغبتهم في توصيل أصواتهم.
And I asked one of the voters, I said, "Whom are you going to vote for?"
سألت أحد الناخبين، قائلا: "لمن ستدلي بصوتك؟"
And he said, "I'm sorry, I can't tell you."
فأجاب قائلا: "آسف، لا يمكنني أن أقول لك ذلك."
He said that his vote was in his heart.
وقال بأن يحتفظ بصوته لنفسه.
And I understood, this was their election,
وأدركت تماما، بأنها إنتخاباتهم،
and they weren't going to let anyone
وأنهم لن ليسمحوا لأي شخص
take it away from them.
بأخذها بعيدا عنهم.
Now the first round of the voting didn't bring forth a clear winner --
جولة التصويت الأولى لم تسفر عن فوز مرشح بصورة واضحة --
so nobody had achieved the absolute majority --
لذا لم يحقق الأغلبية المطلقة --
so voting went into a second round three weeks later.
تم إجراء جولة ثانية من التصويت بعد ثلاثة أسابيع.
The candidates were back on the road; they were campaigning.
عاد المرشحون مرة أخرى للشوارع; لإجراء الحملات الإنتخابية.
The rhetoric of the candidates, of course, changed.
وبالتأكيد فقد تغير خطاب المرشحين.
The heat was on.
إحتدمت المنافسة.
And then the cliche came to haunt us.
وبدأت الأفكار المبتذلة تلاحقنا.
There were claims of intimidation
كانت هناك إدعاءات ترهيبية
at the polling stations,
بمراكز الإقتراع،
of ballot boxes being stolen.
لسرقة صناديق الإقتراع.
Inflated results started coming in
بدأت يأتي تضخم النتائج
and the mob was starting to get out of control.
وبدأت الجماهير في الخروج عن السيطرة.
We witnessed the eruption of violence in the streets.
لقد شهدنا إندلاع أعمال العنف في الشوارع.
People were being beaten brutally.
تم ضرب الناس بوحشية.
The army started firing their guns. People were scrambling.
وحينما بدأت القوات المسلحة بإطلاق الرصاص، تدافع الناس في جميع الإتجاهات.
It was complete chaos.
وعمت الفوضى.
And my heart sank,
ولقد أصبت بخيبة أمل،
because I thought, here we are again.
لأنني أعتقدت، بأننا أمام نفس المشهد السابق مرة أخرى.
Here is another proof
وهذا هو دليل آخر
that the African is not capable of governing himself.
بأن الأفارقة ليسوا قادرين على حكم أنفسهم بنفسهم.
And not only that, I am documenting it --
وليس ذلك فحسب، بل لقد قمت بتوثيقها --
documenting my own cultural shortcomings.
توثيق أوجه القصور الثقافي.
So when the echo of the gunshots
لذلك عندما بدأ يتواني
had lingered,
صدى الطلقات النارية،
it was soon drowned by the chanting of the mob,
بدأ بعدها يظهر هتاف الشعب،
and I didn't believe what I was hearing.
لم أصدق ما كنت أسمعه.
They were chanting, "We want peace.
إنهم يرددون، " نريد السلام.
We want peace."
نريد السلام."
And I realized it had to come from the people.
أدركت بأنه يجب أن يأتي من الشعب.
After all, they decide,
وبعد كل شيء، لقد قرروا،
and they did.
وفعلوا.
So the sounds that were before distorted and loud,
والأصوات التي كانت من قبل مرتفعة ومشوهة،
were suddenly a melody.
فجأة صارت لحنا.
The sounds of the voices were harmonious.
الأصوات كانت ألفاظا صوتية منسجمة.
So it could happen.
لذا يمكن أن تحدث.
A democracy could be upheld peacefully.
يمكن أن تؤيد الديمقراطية بصورة سلمية.
It could be, by the will of the masses
يمكن أن يكون ذلك، عبر الجماهير
who were now urgently pressing
التي تلح الآن وبصورة عاجلة
with all their heart and all their will
من قلبها وإرادتها
for peace.
من أجل إحلال السلام.
Now here's an interesting comparison.
والآن هنا مقارنة مثيرة للإهتمام.
We in the West,
نحن في الغرب،
we preach the values,
نحن نبشر بالقيم،
the golden light of democracy,
نور الديمقراطية الذهبي،
that we are the shining example of how it's done.
الذي نعتبر نحن مثالا لأشعته وكيف تم ذلك.
But when it comes down to it,
لكن عندما تأتي إليها،
Ghana found itself in the same place
تجد غانا نفسها في نفس المكان
in which the U.S. election stalled
الذي توفقت فيه إنتخابات الرئاسة بالولايات المتحدة
in the 2000 presidential elections --
في عام 2000م--
Bush versus Gore.
بوش مقابل آل غور.
But instead of the unwillingness of the candidates
لكن بدلا عن عدم رغبة المرشحين
to allow the system to proceed and the people to decide,
السماح بالمضي قدما وترك الشعب يقرر،
Ghana honored democracy
افتخرت غانا بالديمقراطية
and its people.
وشعبها.
It didn't leave it up to the Supreme Court to decide;
إنها لم تتركها للمحكحة العليا لتقرر;
the people did.
الشعب هو الذي فعل ذلك.
Now the second round of voting
والآن الجولة الثانية من االتصويت
did not bring forth a clear winner either.
لم تسفر عن فوز مرشح أيضا.
I mean, it was so incredibly close.
أعني، إن النتائج كانت متقاربة جدا.
The electoral commissioner declared,
أعلنت مفوضية الإنتخابات،
with the consent of the parties,
بموافقة الأحزاب،
to run an unprecedented
إجراء لم يسبق له مثيل
second re-run.
وهو إعادة الجولة الثانية.
So the people went back to the polls
وعاد الشعب مرة أخرة لصناديق الإقتراع
to determine their own president,
لتحديد رئيسهم،
not the legal system.
وليس النظام القانوني.
And guess what, it worked.
وبالفعل، لقد نجح في ذلك.
The defeated candidate
المرشح المهزوم
gave up power
تنازل عن السلطة
and made way for Ghana to move into a new democratic cycle.
فاسحا المجال لغانا بالتحرك نحو دائرة ديمقراطية جديدة.
I mean, at the absolute time
أعني، في الوقت الحاسم
for the absolute need of democracy,
من أجل الحاجة المطلقة للديمقراطية،
they did not abuse their power.
لم يقوموا باساءة إستخدام سلطتهم.
The belief in true democracy and in the people runs deep,
الاعتقاد في الديمقراطية الحقيقية وفي الشعب بصورة عميقة،
proving that the African is capable of governing himself.
يدل على أن الأفارقة لديهم القدرة على حكم بأنفسهم.
Now the uphill battle for Ghana and for Africa
المعركة الشرسة لغانا ولأفريقيا
is not over,
لم تنتهي بعد،
but I have proof that the other side of democracy exists,
لكن لدي إثبات بوجود الجانب الآخر من الديمقراطية،
and that we must not take it for granted.
ويجب علينا ألا نعتبره أمر مفروغ منه.
Now I have learned
لقد تعلمت
that my place is not just in the West or in Africa,
بأن مكاني ليس هو في الغرب أو في أفريقيا،
and I'm still searching
ولازلت أبحث
for my identity,
عن هويتي،
but I saw Ghana
لكني رأيتُ غانا
create democracy better.
إنشات ديمقراطية بصورة أفضل.
Ghana taught me
علمتني غانا
to look at people differently
أن أنظر للناس بطريقة مختلفة
and to look at myself differently.
والنظر إلى نفسي بصورة مختلفة أيضا.
And yes,
نعم،
we Africans can.
يمكننا نحن الأفارقة فعل ذلك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)